So, you know this is our 100th episode.
तो, आपको पता है ये हमारा 100th एपिसोड
Yes, Ansh told me.  Good.  Are you
है। हां, मुझे बताया था अंश ने। अच्छा। आप
happy with my work?  Yes, yes.  Yes.  Sure?
खुश हो मेरे काम से? हां, यस। यस। श्योर?
Because in the middle you were very doubtful.
क्योंकि बीच में तो आप बड़े डाउटफुल थे।
I remain doubtful about everything.  It
डाउटफुल तो मैं हर चीज में रहता हूं। हर
happens in everything.  So, at
चीज में होता है हर चीज में। तो, फिर आप
what point are you sure?  At what point were
श्योर किस पॉइंट पे होते हो? किस पॉइंट पे
you sure?  Tell me about my work.
आप श्योर हुए? मेरे काम को लेके बताओ।
No, I see the results
नहीं मैं जब देखता हूं रिजल्ट उसके उसके
after that.  Good.  So what do you think about the result
बाद में। अच्छा। तो रिजल्ट कैसा दिखता है
?  From your end?
आपको? आपके एंड से?
Then such people tell me that you are Prakhar's
फिर ऐसे लोग मुझे कहते हैं आप प्रखर के
father, I feel very good.
पापा हो तो मुझे बड़ा अच्छा लगता है।
Well, now just like you are
अच्छा तो अभी आप जैसे अभी ये शादीवादी के
making all the wedding bookings etc.,
आप सब बुकिंग वगैरह करा रहे हो वहां पे भी
people recognize you there also.  Yes, I recognise it.
लोग पहचान जाते हैं। हां पहचान जाते हैं।
So you find them because you
तो आपको मिल जाते हैं क्योंकि आप मेरे से
keep asking me whether I found anyone today?  Did you
पूछते रहते हो ना कि कोई मिला आज? कोई
meet anyone today?  Yes, you get them.  Then
मिला आज? हां तो आपको मिल जाते हैं। फिर
why do you ask?  No, I am asking,
क्यों पूछते हो आप? नहीं मैं पूछता हूं
right now I don’t get as much as I should.
अभी उतने नहीं मिलते जितने मिलने चाहिए।
Finish. Stop the podcast.  Come on brother,
खत्म ख़ बंद करो पॉडकास्ट। चलो भाई
finish it.  Did you ever feel afraid in your childhood that
खत्म। आपको कभी ऐसे बचपन में डर लगा था कि
you would slip out of your hands?  No, never on the hands or
मैं हाथ से निकल जाऊंगा? नहीं हाथ पे तो
legs,
पैर
but never on the body, meaning it feels like
कभी नहीं बट कभी भी मतलब ऐसा लगा हो कि
you are understanding something, friend
पता नहीं कुछ आप समझ रहे हो जाता है यार
dad, it must happen like this.  Yes, no,
पापा ऐसे तो होता ही होगा। हां नहीं वो
when the child is 17, 18, 19, 20, 21
बच्चे की जब उम्र होती है 17 18 19 20 21
years old it feels like that and even when he went to America
साल तो लगता है और अमेरिका चले गए थे तो
I was like that.  But now it's alright, that
भी मैं लगा था। लेकिन अब ठीक है फॉल्स वेल
ends well.  Good.  Ok.  So, it felt that way at that time for
दैट एंड्स वेल। अच्छा। ओके। तो, उस टाइम
some reason or just generally
पे किसी वजह से लगा था या बस जनरली
because there is no distance
क्योंकि एक मतलब डिस्टेंस
, because America is a very free
नहीं, अमेरिका में क्योंकि बहुत फ्री
society.  Now you are too free in your thoughts, so
सोसाइटी है। अब तुम अपने विचारों में भी
ignore that.
कुछ ज्यादा ही फ्री हो तो उसको ध्यान ना
So do you still watch all my episodes
रखते हुए। तो अब आप मेरे सारे एपिसोड
or not?  I watch it most of the time.
देखते हो अभी भी कि नहीं देखते आप? अधिकतर
Good.  And you must have
देखता हूं। अच्छा। और आप उनके उस वाले
come to that segment where I
सेगमेंट तक तो आते ही होंगे जहां मैं आपकी
praise you.  No, I have
तारीफ करता हूं। नहीं मैं बहुत दिनों से
n't seen anyone like this for a long time.  Well,
आया नहीं है कोई ऐसा। अच्छा ऐसा वाला
yes, maybe we have seen such segments for a long time
सेगमेंट हां शायद हमने काफी दिनों से ऐसा
but whenever you have seen them,
वाला कुछ सेगमेंट बट जब भी आपने देखा है
how do you feel?  Doesn't that sound okay?
आपको कैसा लगता है? नहीं ठीक लगता है? खुल
Tell me openly friend, what happens if you don't feel okay
के बताओ यार नहीं ठीक लगता है क्या होता
?  No, every child praises his father
है? नहीं हर एक बच्चा अपने पापा की तारीफ
or every child praises his father, do
करता है या तो इस पे हर एक बच्चा करता है
you shame on him?  Yes, he is doing it.
शमक तू करता है? हां कर रहा
So I do it.  No, but still because
है। तो करता हूं। नहीं बट फिर भी क्योंकि
I mean, to a large extent, this is a bit of a similar
मैं काफी हद तक मतलब ये एक ऐसी थोड़ी वैसी
thing, I don't know how you will take it.  To a large
बात है पता नहीं आप कैसे लोगे। मैं काफी
extent, I do my work so that you feel
हद तक अपना काम इसलिए करता हूं ताकि आपको
proud.  In general, I
प्राउड फील हो। इन जनरल एक ओरिएंटेशन उसको
give him such an orientation because I know, you
ऐसी देता हूं क्योंकि मेरे को पता है आप
see, I know, you might like it,
देखते हो मेरे को पता है आपको मतलब अच्छा
you have been thinking from the beginning that
लगता होगा आपको शुरू से यह रहा है कि
Prakhar should name him, so then I give him a level of
प्रखर नाम करे तो फिर मैं एक लेवल ऑफ
orientation that he likes,
ओरिएंटेशन वैसे ही देता हूं उसे हम अच्छा
according to you, what do I do best,
आपके हिसाब से मैं बेस्ट क्या करता हूं
what do I do best in my work, yes, what am I
अपने काम में बेस्ट क्या करता हूं हां
good at,
व्हाट एम आई वै गुड एट
you are good at everything, this Holi or
तुम हर चीज में अच्छे हो ये होली या
podcast or half an hour will only last, you accept it,
पॉडकास्ट या आधा घंटा ही चलेगा तुम मान लो
what better can I do?
और मैं क्या बेटर कर सकता हूं?
First of all, you do not talk to your guest while maintaining eye contact.
एक तो तुम अपने गेस्ट से ना आंख मिला के
Ok, good.  Whereas one
बात नहीं करते हो। अच्छा ठीक है। जबकि
should always talk while looking into the eyes.  Ok.
हमेशा आंख मिला के बात करनी चाहिए। ठीक
And I don't like the abuses etc. that happen in some podcasts.
और कुछ पडकास्ट में जो गाली वगैरह होती है
Ok.  Ok.
वो मुझे पसंद नहीं आती है। ठीक है। ठीक
Well it isn't taken anymore.  Yes.  It does
है। वेल टेकन अब तो नहीं होती। हां। अब
n't happen now.  Yes.  It doesn't happen now.  We
नहीं होती। हां। अब नहीं होती। हम गेस्टों
only refuse guests.  Papa watches our
को ही मना करते हैं। पापा देखते हैं हमारा
podcast so don't give it to me.  Yes.  Ok.  Then
पॉडकास्ट तो मत दो। हां। ठीक है। फिर बाकी
everything else is fine.  Good.  Yes.  So,
तो सब बढ़िया है। अच्छा। हां। तो उस टाइम
how many years ago was that incident at that time?  85 87?
मतलब कितने साल पुरानी बात हो गई? 85 87?
Started practice in 84?  From here.
84 में प्रैक्टिस शुरू की? यहीं से। इसी
In this very office 84 Yes, practically in this very office.
ऑफिस में 84 हां, प्रैक्टिकली इसी ऑफिस
84 and me in 2024.  So,
में। 84 और मैंने 2024 में। तो,
exactly 40 years later, right?
एक्साक्ट्ली 40 इयर्स लेटर है ना?
And you had a scooter then?
और तब आप तब आपके पास स्कूटर होता था?
Describe means we used to say financial.
डिस्क्राइब मतलब हम फाइनेंसियल बोलते थे।
Yes, yes, there was a scooter.  Yes.  Yes.
यस, यस, स्कूटर होता था। हां। हां। 86 में
Bought a car in 86.  Good.  Which car was that?
कार खरीदी थी। अच्छा। कौन सी गाड़ी थी वो?
That was 800?  No Premier Padmini.  You will
वो थी 800? नहीं प्रीमियर पद्मिनी। एक बार
install it once, you will be impressed by how the Premier Padmani looks, you will
लगाएगा प्रीमियर पद्मनी कैसी दिखती है इस
drink water from it, right? Yes, it was like this, the second one, this
पे आ जाएगा पानी पियोगे ना ये हां ऐसी थी
second one, the
वो सेकंड ये वाली सेकंड वाली सेकंड वाली
blue one, yes, yes, I
ब्लू वाली जो है हां हां अच्छा
bought it for ₹00, yes and then initially I did
₹00 में खरीदी थी हां और फिर शुरू में
not have money, so I picked it up and kept it in Mathura, I
पैसे नहीं थे तो उसको मथुरा उठा के रख आए
could not drive it because yes
थे कि चला नहीं सकते थे क्योंकि हां
because people would ask where the car was parked, so that is why I got it
क्योंकि लोग पूछते थे गाड़ी खड़ी की हुई
parked at my uncle's house
है तो इसलिए ताऊजी के घर खड़ी कराए मथुरा
in Mathura, as if no one would ask,
में जैसे कोई पूछे नहीं वो पूछेंगे तो
what will happen if they ask?  I don't know, just in the beginning there was
क्या हो जाएगा? पता नहीं बस शुरू शुरू में
a little more consciousness.  Okay,
थोड़ी कॉन्शियसनेस ज्यादा होती थी। अच्छा
so he was made to stand there and then
तो उसको वहां खड़ा करा है और फिर
how did he go to the clients or how did he do it
क्लाइंटों के पास कैसे जाते थे या कैसे
?  Used to go by scooter.  Well, I would have
करते थे? स्कूटर से जाते थे। अच्छा स्कूटर
gone by scooter.  And what year did you first
से जाते थे। एंड व्हाट ईयर डीड यू फर्स्ट
start seeing success papa?  When did your
स्टार्ट सीइंग सक्सेस पापा? व्हेन डीड योर
life start changing?  Because you see,
लाइफ स्टार्ट चेंजिंग? बिकॉज़ आपने देखो
I remember in the first year, we had
तो पहले साल में मुझे याद है
8485, we got aggregate receipt of the
8485 वी हैव गॉट एग्रीगेट रिसीप्ट ऑफ़ द
year, about 6070 at that time, it used to be
ईयर अबाउट 6070 एट दैट टाइम इट यूज़्ड टू
reasonably well because whatever we used to get in the job,
बी रीज़नेबली वेल बिकॉज़ नौकरी में भी जो
a chartered accountant, a fresh
मिलते थे हमको ए चार्टर्ड अकाउंटेंट फ्रेश
chartered accountant used to get only ₹34000 per month.
चार्टर्ड अकाउंटेंट को ₹34000 महीने ही
So by that standard is
मिला करते थे। तो बाय दैट स्टैंडर्ड इज़
good and I remember in 1989, first four
गुड एंड आई रिमेंबर इन 1989 फर्स्ट फोर
months from April to July, I
मंथ्स फ्रॉम अप्रैल टू जुलाई आई
mean our receipts were aggregated to ₹ 1 lakh
मीन आवर रिसीट्स वर एग्रीगेटेड टू ₹1 लाख
of we were very happy, we, me and Rajji Tau
ऑफ वी वर वेरी हैप्पी हम मी एंड राजजी ताऊ
ji, we are very
जी हम वी आर वेरी
happy, we have, we have stuck well, and
हैप्पी वी हैव वी हैव स्टक वेल हम एंड
but
बट
I find each and every person very lovely, I like it
मुझे हर एक व्यक्ति बहुत हीकि प्यारा लगता
from the heart, so
है अच्छा लगता है दिल से हम तो इसलिए
things keep getting added on and then
चीजें जुड़ती चली जाती हैं और फिर
technically also we kept ourselves up to date
टेक्निकली भी अपने आप को हम अप टू डेट
, kept ourselves sound.  Whoever we could help, wherever we could, we would help them.
रखते थे, साउंड रखते थे। जिसकी जहां हेल्प
And God has been very kind.  Blessings
एंड गॉड हैज़ बीन वेरी काइंड। ब्लेसिंग्स
of parents.  This matters a lot in life.
ऑफ़ पेरेंट्स। ये लाइफ में बहुत मैटर करता
To my mind.  I have
है। टू माय माइंड। मैंने आपसे ज्यादा
never seen a man more hardworking than you.  And
मेहनती आदमी तो नहीं देखा। और यह बात तो
people in your office also kept telling me this.
मेरे को लोग आपके ऑफिस के भी कहते रहे।
Like Rishabh Bhaiya or those people who said this is
जैसे ऋषभ भैया थे या जो लोग थे कि दिस इज
unique about your father.  And then for me it
यूनिक अबाउट योर फादर। और मेरे को तब तो
becomes a matter of family.  But even today you
घर की घर वाली बात हो जाती है। पर आप आज
wake up at 5:00 am.  Yes, I wake up before 5
भी 5:00 बजे उठ जाते हो। हां 5 से पहले उठ
even today and by 10:00 pm at night
जाता हूं आज भी और रात को 10:00 बजे तक तो
you are not even in a condition to talk, you pass
आप बात करने की हालत में भी नहीं होते
out, I mean, Papa and
बिल्कुल पास आउट हो जाते हो मतलब पापा और
I sitting together literally just say, you are
मेरा साथ में बैठना लिटरली सिर्फ ये होता
fine, you are fine, while doing that, Papa
है ठीक हो ठीक हो उतने करते-करते पापा
starts snoring, he does not even know that it is
ख्राटे ले रहे हैं उन्हें पता ही नहीं है
okay because he gets tired and my
ठीक है क्योंकि थक जाते हैं और मेरे को
mother told me sir, you told me, Mummy
मम्मी मम्मी ने बताया सर आपने बताया मम्मी
told me that when you had
ने बताया कि जब आप शुरू में लीगल
started doing legal practice in the beginning, you used to take the entire file and
प्रैक्टिस करने लगे थे तो आप पूरी फाइल ले
read it, you used to memorize it, I do
लेके पढ़ा करते थे उसे रटा करते थे अभी
not read it now, you used to memorize your entire argument
पढ़ता हूं नहीं आप अपना पूरा वो आर्गुमेंट
which you will give tomorrow, yes yes because because I have
जो आप कल दोगे वो रटा करते थे यस यस बिकॉज़
studied in Hindi medium
बिकॉज़ आई हैव स्टडीड इन हिंदी मीडियम
school and arguments have to be made in
स्कूल एंड आर्गुमेंट्स हैव टू बी मेड इन
English.  So I did not have enough
इंग्लिश। हम सो आई डिड नॉट हैव एडिकेट
confidence that whether I would be able to
कॉन्फिडेंस कि वेदर आई विल बी एबल टू
speak.  So I used to write it down and memorize it roughly and
स्पीक। तो मैं तो लिख के और रफली रट लेता
when I used to argue and that too, by
था हम और जब आर्ग्यू करता था और वो भी बाय
heart used to, even now it so happens even now
हर्ट यूज्ड टू अभी भी इट सो हैपेंस इवन
before some strange benches, stranger benches
नाउ आल्सो बिफोर सम स्ट्रेंज बेंचेस
across the country, when I go to
स्ट्रेंजर बेंचेस अक्रॉस द कंट्री व्हेन
new judges, I do not know them, that
आई गो नए जजेस तो मुझे जानते नहीं हम तो
is why sometimes I feel at the age of 62 also
इसलिए समटाइ्स आई फील एट द एज ऑफ़ 62 आल्सो
my heart throbs on us, it must be fun
माय हर्ट थ्रोब्स हम पर उससे मजा आता होगा
otherwise what will be the fun left, there is no
वरना फिर मजा क्या रह जाएगा काम में नहीं
fun in the work, the fun begins if we win, after that.
मजा आता है यदि जीत जाते हैं उसके उसके
And there is stress due to stress.
और स्ट्रेस स्ट्रेस को लेके स्ट्रेस तो
Yes.  But you don't mind.   If
होता है। हां। पर आप माइंड नहीं करते।
you mind it then there is no option.  Either
माइंड कर लोगे तो देयर इज़ नो ऑप्शन। या तो
you are or you are not, either you are
आप यू आर और यू आर नॉट या तो आप प्रोफेशन
in profession or you are not.  Because without stress you
में हो या नहीं हो। बिकॉज़ बिना स्ट्रेस के
cannot achieve this rate of success.  This
फिर सक्सेस की ये रेट नहीं मिलती। मेरा ये
is my belief.  Although there may be divergent
मानना है। हालांकि देयर मे बी डायवर्जेंट
views on it.  But I
व्यूज ऑन इट। तो लेकिन मैं सक्सेस के बाद
enjoy that stress after success.  After the success
उस स्ट्रेस को एंजॉय करता हूं। सक्सेस के
[MUSIC].  What is that one
[संगीत]
thing you have learnt from your grandfather
बाद। आपने दादा जी से एक ऐसी क्या चीज
which has helped you throughout your life?
सीखी है जो आपको पूरी लाइफ हेल्प करी है।
That one should not break anyone's trust.  Dada ji
कि विश्वास किसी का नहीं तोड़ना। दादा जी
always says that if someone has trusted
हमेशा कहते हैं हम कि इफ समबडी हैज़
you then you must ensure that the
ट्रस्टेड यू देन यू मस्ट एनश्योर दैट ह
trust remains intact.
ट्रस्ट रिमेंस इंटैक्ट।
Never ever backstep
नेवर एवर बैकस्टप
anybody. This teaching and commitment from grandfather
एनीबडी यह दादा जी की यह सीख और कमिटमेंट
that whatever you say to someone, fulfill those words,
कि जो कह दिया किसी को वो शब्दों को पूरा
fulfill the promise no matter what the
करो वचन को पूरा करो चाहे उसमें कुछ भी
cost is. What is that thing that you learnt from me and Amma
कॉस्ट आए हम और अम्मा से ऐसी क्या चीज
which helped you throughout your life?
सीखे आप जो आपको सारी लाइफ हेल्प की?
I learnt from Amma to love everyone with all my heart.
अम्मा से सीखा मैंने कि सबको दिल से प्यार
And don't think that I will get any
करो। और यह मत सोचो कि मेरा इसमें कोई
benefit from this, I won't.
फायदा होगा, नहीं
I learnt this from my mother.
होगा। ये चीज मैंने अम्मा से सीखी। आपको
What do you think?  What did you do well in
क्या लगता है? व्हाट डिड यू डू वेल इन
parenting me?
पैरेंटिंग मी?
I have taught you good things since childhood.
मैंने तुमको बचपन से अच्छी-अच्छी बातें
Stories have been taught.  And whether
सिखाई हैं। कहानियां सिखाई हैं। और चाहे
it is from Mahabharata or
वो महाभारत की रही हो, चाहे वो पंचतंत्र
from Panchatantra.  Yes.
से रही हो। हां।
And whatever time I could have spent with you,
और जितना टाइम मैंने तुम्हारे साथ दिया है
I am sad that I did
मुझे इस बात का दुख है कि मैंने राधिका के
not spend with Radhika.  Do you like Radhika more than pyaari
साथ नहीं दिया। प्यारी आपको राधिका ज्यादा
?  No, that's fine.
लगती है? नहीं वो तो ठीक है। प्यारी तो
Both of them are lovely.  Radhika is really lovely.
दोनों ही है। राधिका तो है ही प्यारी।
Yes.  And but one thing is because by the time
हां। और लेकिन एक बात का बिकॉज़ उस वक्त तक
you were growing up I probably did
जब तुम बड़े हो रहे थे मेरे पास शायद काम
not have that much work engagement.
की इतनी एंगेजमेंट नहीं थी। हम
After Radhika was born, my workload increased and I was
राधिका जब हुई उसके बाद काम बढ़ गया तो मैं
not able to give her that much time.  So let's go now, I mean
उतना समय नहीं दे पाया। हम तो चलो अब तो
we can't go back, no yes yes yes
आई मीन वी कैन नॉट गो बैक नो हां हां हां
but I would agree because I think
बट आई वुड एग्री क्योंकि आई थिंक जितना भी
whatever I am able to talk about, to a
जो भी मैं बात भी कर पाता हूं उसका उस
large extent its corpus was that every night
बहुत हद तक कॉर्पस वो ये था कि रोज रात को
before going to sleep, you used to tell me a story
सोने से पहले आप मेरे को एक कहानी सुनाते
and make me pray and I used to make you pray,
थे और एक प्रेयर कराता था मैं एक प्रेयर
that prayer had a lot of impact, do you
कराते थे उस प्रेयर का बहुत इम्पैक्ट आपको
remember the prayer?  I neither remembered it then nor do I
प्रेयर याद है? मेरे को तो ना तब याद हुई
remember it today.  My
ना आज याद है। मेरे को तो मैं कम से कम
father must have made me do that prayer every day for at least three-four years.
तीन-चार साल रोज पापा ने वो प्रेयर कराई
I never remembered it.
होगी। मेरे को कभी याद ही नहीं हुई।
Because they pray so forcefully, let me
क्योंकि इतनी जबरदस्ती वो प्रेयर करते हैं
sleep, just let me sleep brother.  Yes, but
कि सोने दो बस सोने दो भाई। हां पर रोज
prayers were held every night.  Shamak remembers Shamak
रात को प्रेयर होती थी। शमक को याद है शमक
saying that I will be a good boy.
कह रहा है कि मैं मैं अच्छा बच्चा बनूंगा।
I will not fight with anyone.  I will
मैं किसी से नहीं लडूंगा। मैं किसी से
not fight with anyone.  All things are
नहीं लडूंगा। ऑल थिंग्स आर
true.  I will love my younger sister Radhika very much.
ट्रू। मैं अपनी छोटी बहन राधिका से बहुत
That is true.  That is true.  Yes.
प्यार करूंगा। वो सच है। वो सच है। हां।
And then you should tell me that I should obey everyone, I should
और तब आप मेरे को मैं सभी का कहना मानूं,
obey the elders.  Apart from all these things,
बड़ों का कहना मानूं। ये सारी बातें तो और
I also used to say that when I grow up, I will
एक उसमें ये भी मैं कहता था कि बड़े होके
become the Chief Justice of India.  He used to say this also.
चीफ जस्टिस ऑफ़ इंडिया बनूंगा। ये भी कहता
That is deserted.  That dream is gone.
था। वो तो डेजर्टेड है। वो ड्रीम तो गया।
Baba, I cannot become a good judge.  My
मैं बाबा अच्छा जज नहीं बन पाता। मेरा
mouth is wide open.
मुंह ज्यादा खुला हुआ है।
What do you think mommy did?
आपको लगता है मम्मी ने क्या करा?
Good parenting with us.  The
पेरेंटिंग में अच्छा हमारे साथ। मम्मी का
affection that mom has for you guys or
तो जो जो अफेक्शन है तुम लोगों के लिए या
for the entire family is very pure.
पूरी फैमिली के लिए हम वो बड़ा प्योर है।
I can't describe the intensity of that and me.
हम और वो उसकी इंटेंसिटी को मैं बयान नहीं
He maintained
कर सकता। वो अपनी फैमिली के लिए अपने
his career for the sake of his family and his children for so many years that
बच्चों के लिए अपना करियर उसने इतने साल
his children would grow up.
तक करके रखा कि मेरे बच्चे बड़े होंगे।
First of all, I have children whom I have to
सबसे पहले तो मेरे बच्चे हैं जिनको मैंने
raise.  She did not even come to the office.   She did
बड़ा करना है। वो ऑफिस भी नहीं आती थी।
n’t even practice.  When we
प्रैक्टिस भी नहीं करती थी। हम जब तुम
grew up, she thought, let me
बड़े हुए तो उन्होंने सोचा कि चलो मैं अब
do something now.  So his sacrifice is
कुछ करती हूं। तो उसका जो सैक्रिफाइस है
for the family, not only to her children but
फैमिली के लिए नॉट ओनली टू हर चिल्ड्रन बट
to my family, my extended family, I am
टू माय फैमिली माय एक्सटेंडेड फैमिली आई
us,
मेंस हम
and
और
selflessly, he has no selfish motive of any kind.  There
सेल्फलेसली उसका कोई कोई किसी तरह का उसको
is no meaning in being with your children.  She does everything for her Even Family and
होने का मतलब ही नहीं है। इवन फैमिली और
extended family with the same
एक्सटेंडेड फैमिली के लिए भी वो उतने ही
dedication as she does for all of us.  Be
मनोयोग से करती है जितना कि वो हम सबके
it my sisters or
लिए करती है। हम चाहे वो मेरी सिस्टर्स
anyone else.  We are my cousin brothers and their
हो, चाहे कोई भी हो। हम मेरे कजिन ब्रदर्स
families.   Do
हो, उनकी फैमिलीज हो।
you think I'll go away again
आपको अब ऐसा लगता है कि मैं फिर दूर चला
?  Yes, do you know the fear?  Are
जाऊंगा? हां, डर मालूम है? डर लगता है
you scared of this?  No, I am not scared.
आपको इस बात का? नहीं डर तो नहीं लगता।
I know.  Well, you know I will go.
मुझे मालूम है। अच्छा आपको मालूम है चला
Why?  Why do you know?  You are
जाऊंगा। क्यों? क्यों मालूम है? तुम्हारी
also
शादी भी
getting married to your Clau, who is Mexican.
तुम्हारी क्लाऊ से हो रही है जो मेक्सिकन
Yes.  And I know that you are
है। हां। और ये तो मालूम है कि तुम जितने
with me for the seven days I am with you.  Otherwise,
सात दिन साथ हो उससे हो। वरना तो फिर हम
Mom and I will be alone.  Good.  I will leave you alone and go away.
और मम्मी अकेले रहेंगे। अच्छा। अकेले छोड़
Kshama will see it
के चला जाऊंगा मैं। क्षमा देख लेगा पीछे
from behind.  Yes, he will handle it.  No, where will
से। हां, वो हैंडल कर लेगा। नहीं, कहां
I go?  I will go at least a little bit.
जाऊंगा मैं? थोड़ा बहुत तो चला ही जाऊंगा।
No, go and fly as much as you can, what's the big
नहीं जाओ जितना उड़ सकते हो उड़ो इसमें क्या
deal in it, now if you want to
बात है अब तरक्की करनी है करो हम
progress, do it, to move ahead you have to leave the previous steps,
आगे बढ़ने के लिए पीछे की सीढ़ी छोड़नी होती
this was taught to me, if you have to climb the next step, the upper step, then you will have to
है ये मुझे सिखाया था यदि आगे की सीढ़ी ऊपर
leave the lower one, I
की सीढ़ी चढ़नी है तो नीचे की तो छोड़नी
remember, earlier I used to go to
पड़ेगी ना हम मुझे ध्यान है मैं पहले
Commissioner Appeal, there was
कमिश्नर अपील जाया करता था ट्राइबनल जाने
problem in going to tribunal because there used to be one or two cases there,
में दिक्कत होती थी बिकॉज़ वहां एक दो केस
then our KC Singhal saheb
होते थे हम फिर केसी सिंघल साहब जो हैं
said that Rakesh, if you want to climb the upper step, then you will
हमारे उन्होंने कहा कि राकेश ऊपर की सीढ़ी
have to leave the lower one.
चढ़नी है तो नीचे की तो छोड़नी पड़ेगी।
Then you will have to give up attachment.  In this way, it
मोह मोह छोड़ना पड़ेगा फिर। हम तो इस तरह
applies to every aspect of life.
से लाइफ के हर हर पहलू पर अप्लाई होता है।
go ahead.  Yes, I also feel that
आगे बढ़ो। हां मेरे को भी लगता है कि मेरा
whatever my mission is, it will take me somewhere.
मिशन जितना है वो मेरे को कहीं लेके
Now that thing happens.
जाएगा। अब वो वाली बात हो जाती है।
See, always progress and do
देखो हमेशा तरक्की करो और दूसरे का किसी
no harm to others.  Do as much as you can.
का नुकसान ना हो। जितना कर सकते हो करो।
In what gives you happiness, in what feels good.
जिसमें खुशी मिलती हो जिसमें अच्छा लगता
But no one else should suffer any loss or
हो। लेकिन किसी दूसरे का ना नुकसान हो ना
trouble.  Uncle ji taught me.
दूसरे को तकलीफ हो। ताऊ जी ने सिखाया।
Yes.
हां।
I have learnt many things in life from Tauji.
मैंने ताऊ जी से जिंदगी में बहुत कुछ
So one of the lessons from that was
चीजें सीखी हैं। तो उसमें से एक सीख ये
that when you start saying more in fewer words,
थी कि जब आप कम शब्दों में ज्यादा बात
then that is it.  Now, I used to follow him a lot.
लगो तो वो है। अब जैसे मैं बड़ा फॉलो करता
Arun Jaitley sir used to say.  We used to
था उसको। अरुण जैतली साहब बोलते थे। हम वो
say it so to the point and it was so
इतना टू द पॉइंट बोलते थे और और इतना
relevant.  He used to say Revent only.   He did
रेलेवेंट होता था। वो रेवेंट ही बोलते थे।
not say anything irrelevant and was concise.
इरिलेवेंट तो बोलते ही नहीं थे और कंसाइज।
So Tau ji always says that you should
तो ताऊ जी हमेशा कहते हैं कि आप किसी चीज
bring something in nuclear form.
को न्यूक्लियर फॉर्म में ले आओ।
How much power does a nuclear bomb have?
न्यूक्लियर में कितनी ताकत होती है। हम तो
You make the nuclear weapon and then blast it.
न्यूक्लियर आप बना लो और फिर उससे ब्लास्ट
We will
करो। हम
articulate things as Shak said, now
तो चीजों को आर्टिकुलेट जो शक ने कहा अभी
we will articulate things in fewer words
हम चीजों को आर्टिकुलेट कम शब्दों में आप
and add weight to it.  Uncle ji
कर कर और उसमें वजन पैदा करो। ताऊ जी एक
says one more thing.  There should be
एक बात और कहते हैं। हम
weight in our words, not in our voice; we are
कि बात में वजन हो आवाज में नहीं हम
right, the thing is right, the
ठीक बात ठीक है ना
rest are peripheral things, the substance is the matter; I
बात बाकी तो पेरिफेरल चीजें हैं सब्सटेंस
learnt a lot in life from Tau ji and what did I learn
बहुत कुछ सीखा और क्या सीखा
from Tau ji, one thing I learnt is that
ताऊ जी से एक तो मैंने ये कि कोई भी चीज
before doing anything, write it down; brain is very
है करने से पहले लिखो अच्छा ब्रेन इज वेरी
precious; what are the things to be done to remember this
प्रेशियस इसको याद करने के लिए चीजें
?  what to do?  Don't misutilize
क्या-क्या करने हैं? व्हाट टू डू? उस टू
it to remember those to-do things.
डू थिंग्स को याद करने के लिए आप उसको
Ok?  Is it okay?
मिसयटिलाइज नहीं करो। ठीक है? ठीक है ना?
He is very creative.  Keep him thinking about other things.
वो बड़ा क्रिएटिव है। उसको तो बाकी चीजों
Put it to planning.  Put it for execution.  But to
रखो। एग्जीक्यूशन के लिए रखो। लेकिन ये
think about this, first write down the tasks that need to be done.
सोचने के लिए क्या-क्या काम करने हैं पहले
[Music]
[संगीत]
Secondly, whatever the parents said,
दूसरा कि पेरेंट्स ने जो बोल दिया यह
I learnt it from my uncle.  I also did
मैंने ताऊ जी से सीखा। मैं भी मम्मी पापा
n't listen to my mom and dad that much.  So one day my uncle
की बात उतना नहीं मानता था। तो एक दिन ताऊ
said, friend, you
जी ने कहा यार तू इनकी
talk about them, parents are a very weak link.
बात ये तो बहुत कमजोर कड़ी होती है
So if you have the strength, then
पेरेंट्स। तो हम यदि तुझ में ताकत है तो
fight the world.  These are very
दुनिया से लड़ के दिखा। ये तो दे आर वेरी
tender heart persons.  So from that day
टेंडर हर्ट पर्संस। तो उस दिन के बाद से
onwards I never avoided what mom and dad said, I
फिर मैंने जो मम्मी पापा की बात को मैंने
learnt a lot from my uncle and I also learnt think
बहुत सीखा ताऊ जी से और भी मैंने सीखा
big, what do we think
बड़ा सोचो हम
big in small things, if you
क्या छोटी-छोटी चीजों में बड़ा सोचो बड़ा
think big then you will do big, I
सोचोगे तो बड़ा करोगे हम नहीं मेरे को
think this is yes and always stay positive, it is a
लगता है ये वाली हां और हमेशा पॉजिटिव रहो
good thing, which helps, keep doing it, keep doing it, it will come
अच्छी चीज है जिसकी हेल्प होती है करते
back to you on its own, you should believe that you are
वापस आ जाएगी आपको आप यह मान लो कि आप टू
selfish that whatever you are
दैट टेक्स्ट यू आर सेल्फिश कि आप अच्छा जो
doing good will ultimately come back, but even if it does
कर रहे हो अल्टीमेटली वापस आएगा लेकिन ये
n't come back, keep doing it, we are fine,
ना भी आए तो भी करते रहो हम हम ठीक
wherever I have reached now, I have
है जहां अभी पहुंचा हूं वो भी इसीलिए
reached because of your blessings, this
पहुंचा हूं क्योंकि आप लोगों का आशीर्वाद
house has been made by Amma, this is Amma's house, nothing
है अम्मा का बनाया हुआ घर है अम्मा का घर
else can happen here,
है ये अम्मा तो यहां तो कुछ और हो ही नहीं
Papa, there will only be progress here and wherever I
सकता पापा यहां तो तरक्की ही होगी और जहां
go, I will carry this, yes
जाऊंगा तो यही कैरी करूंगा हां
always bless us, not only them, no,
हमेशा आप आशीर्वाद दो हमें भी इनको भी
everyone is blessed, we have blessings, Bhaiya
नहीं नहीं सबको आशीर्वाद है हमारा तो भैया
and I don't have anything apart from this, get that
और हम पे कुछ है नहीं इसके अलावा
laddu, parents,
अरे वो मंगा लो लड्डू पेरेंट्स के पास
elders have this, son and
एल्डर्स के पास तो यही होता है बेटा और
I have seen that this is the only thing we have in life
मैंने देखा बस सिर्फ यही है जिंदगी में हम
Difference differentiates, it brings a difference
जो डिफरेंस डिफरेंशिएट करता है डिफरेंस
in life, which means whoever takes the blessings of elders,
में जो मतलब बड़ों का जो आशीर्वाद ले लेगा
parents, see, everyone has bad things
पेरेंट्स का देखो बुराई तो हर एक में होती
but take the good things.  Hmm.
है लेकिन अच्छाई चीज अच्छी चीज लो। हम्म।
Take any good thing from anyone.
किसी से भी अच्छी चीज लो।
What is the laddu for?  Just completed 100 episodes.   We
लड्डू किस लिए है? बस 100 एपिसोड्स हो गए।
will make it sweet, please calm it down.  Give it to brother Shamak
मीठा करेंगे शमक करा दे। भाई शमक को दो
first.  Yes shmak shmak.  Come come inside come
पहले। हां शमक शमक। आजा आजा अंदर आजा
in the frame.
फ्रेम में आजा।
So far there have only been 100.  Yes.  Good.   I have
तो अभी तक 100 ही हुए हैं। हां। अच्छा।
made good progress, just
अच्छी तरक्की किया है 100 के हिसाब से
not 100%.  No, I thought it was too much.
नहीं। नहीं मैं समझ रहा था कि ज्यादा हो
No
गए हैं। नहीं
no, you also take it.   Are
नहीं तू भी ले।
we making good progress as per 100 or
हम 100 के हिसाब से अच्छी तरक्की है कि
not, we are fine,
नहीं हम सही है
come on bro, I may
चलो ब्रो मैं
not be, I am a little
ना मे बी आई एम अ लिटिल
too
टू
idealistic but whatever I am, whatever I am, whatever I will be, I will
आइडियलिस्टिक बट मैं जो कुछ भी हूं
be because my father, mother, my sister, my
बिकॉज़ मेरे पापा मम्मी मेरी बहन, मेरे
grandparents, the rest of my family, my brother,
दादा-दादी, मेरी बाकी फैमिली, मेरे भैया,
my uncle, my aunt, these people are with me.
मेरे ताऊ जी, मेरी ताई जी ये लोग मेरे साथ
His blessings are with me.  And
हैं। इनका आशीर्वाद मेरे साथ है। और
frankly this feeling alone has given
फ्रैंकली दिस फीलिंग अलोन हैज़ गिवेन
me so much pain through what has been a
मी सो मच करज थ्रू व्हाट हैज़
very hard journey.  I remember when
बीन अ वेरी हार्ड जर्नी। आई रिमेंबर जब
I left America and came here, I used to be
मैं अमेरिका छोड़ के यहां आया था, मेरे को
so stressed about how this would happen?
कितना स्ट्रेस रहता था कि यह कैसे बनेगा?
How will we do it?  Right?  And now we are
हाउ विल वी डू इट? राइट? एंड नाउ वी आर
100 episodes deep since I got back.  100
100 एपिसोड्स डीप सिंस आई गॉट बैक। 100
episodes.  I don't have any memory of
एपिसोड्स। आई डोंट हैव एनी मेमोरी ऑफ कि
when those 100 episodes were completed.  And in
वो 100 एपिसोड कब-कब में हो गए। एंड इन
that we have done what is the number Govind?
दैट वी हैव डन व्हाट इज द नंबर गोविंद?
900 and 4 million views on YouTube alone.
900 एंड 4 मिलियन व्यूज ऑन YouTube अलोन।
In a 100 episodes, we've done about 10 crore
इन अ 100 एपिसोड्स, वीव डन अबाउट 10 करोड़
plus views on long form content alone.
प्लस व्यूज़ ऑन लॉन्ग फॉर्म कंटेंट अलोन।
Over the last 100 episodes.  We've
ओवर द लास्ट 100 एपिसोड्स। वी हैव
done about 80 crore 80 crore views on shots
डन अबाउट 80 करोड़ 80 करोड़ व्यूज ऑन शॉट्स
sorry 80 crore views on shots over the last
सॉरी 80 करोड़ व्यूज ऑन शॉट्स ओवर द लास्ट
100 episodes and it has been a fantastic
100 एपिसोड्स एंड इट हैज़ बीन अ फैंटास्टिक
journey bringing you on to some of the best
जर्नी ब्रिंगिंग यू ऑन टू सम ऑफ़ द बेस्ट
conversations I've had over the last one
कन्वर्सेशंस आई हैव हैड ओवर द लास्ट वन
year you've seen us cry on this
ईयर आपने हमें रोते हुए देखा है इस
podcast.  You've seen us laughing
पॉडकास्ट पे। आपने हमें हंसते हुए देखा है
on this podcast.  I've probably
इस पॉडकास्ट पे। शायद हंसते हुए रोते हुए
seen a lot more laughing and crying on this podcast.
से बहुत ज्यादा देखा है इस पॉडकास्ट पे।
And I want your life to
और मैं चाहता हूं आपकी लाइफ भी उतनी ही
be as full of laughter as there is laughter on this podcast.
हंसी हो जितनी हंसी इस पॉडकास्ट पे रही
And look at the little tears, it's a
है। और थोड़े-थोड़े आंसू तो देखो इट्स अ
part of it.  Right?  Over the last 100
पार्ट ऑफ इट। राइट? ओवर द लास्ट 100
episodes we've tried to take four broad
एपिसोड्स हमने वी ट्राइड टू टेक फोर ब्रॉड
themes we wanted to play with.  We Took
थीम्स वी वांटेड टू प्ले विद। वी टूक
Family.  We insisted upon family?  I would ask that
फैमिली। वी इंसिस्टेड अपॉन फैमिली? आई वुड
question over and over.  So House
आस्क दैट क्वेश्चन ओवर एंड ओवर। सो हाउस
Your Relationship With Your Parents Growing
योर रिलेशनशिप विथ योर पेरेंट्स ग्रोइंग
Up?  In that, in the beginning you put a
अप? उसमें आपने शुरू में यू पुट अ
dedication for your father?  How was your
डेडिकेशन फॉर योर फादर? हाउ वास् योर
relationship with him?  Sir,
रिलेशनशिप विथ हिम? आपके सर, आपका आपकी
how has been your relationship with your mother?  We
मम्मी के साथ रिलेशनशिप कैसा रहा है? वी
take your relationship with God.  And what is
टूक योर रिलेशनशिप विथ गॉड। एंड व्हाट इज
your relationship with God?  Are you a God
योर रिलेशनशिप विथ गॉड? आर यू अ गॉड
fearing We ask questions about your
फियरिंग वी आस्क क्वेश्चंस अबाउट योर
vulnerability Your fears.  What is your
वल्लनरेबिलिटी योर फियर्स। व्हाट इज योर
life's biggest fear brother?  Okay,
लाइफ्स बिगेस्ट फियर भाई? अच्छा मेरे को
tell me one thing, what is the biggest fear in your life
एक बात बता तेरा लाइफ का सबसे बड़ा डर क्या
?  And we ask questions about
है? एंड वी आस्क क्वेश्चंस अबाउट
friendship.  How were your friends etc., Sir?
फ्रेंडशिप। दोस्त वगैरह कैसे थे सर आपके?
I tried to do over the first 100
आई ट्राइड टू डू ओवर द फर्स्ट 100
episodes over the first 900 million
एपिसोड्स ओवर द फर्स्ट 900 मिलियन करोड़
how much is in crore?  90 crores.  Almost 100
में कितना होता है? 90 करोड़। ऑलमोस्ट 100
crore views.  100 crore views.  I try to
करोड़ व्यू। 100 करोड़ व्यूज। आई ट्राई टू
ground myself.  In a very stressful
ग्राउंड मायसेल्फ। इन अ वेरी स्ट्रेसफुल
position that I was in on two things that
पोजीशन दैट आई वास इन ऑन टू थिंग्स दैट
last for ever.
लास्ट फॉर एवर।
Your family, the memories of them, the lessons you
योर फैमिली, द मेमोरीज ऑफ देम, द लेसंस यू
learn from them, your friends, your God
लर्न फ्रॉम देम, योर फ्रेंड्स, योर गॉड
and your
एंड योर
fears.  And now now that 100 episodes are
फियर्स। एंड नाउ नाउ दैट 100 एपिसोड्स आर
over, what was once Prakhar's discourse is
ओवर, व्हाट वाज़ वंस प्रखर के प्रवचन इज़
now
नाउ
PGX.  Now there is going to be a new
पीजीएक्स। नाउ देयर इज़ गोइंग टू बी अ न्यू
story.  And I am going to tell you a new
स्टोरी। एंड आई एम गोइंग टू टेल यू अ न्यू
story.  And if you stay here, if you
स्टोरी। एंड इफ यू स्टे हियर, इफ यू
subscribe, if you watch my content again,
सब्सक्राइब, इफ यू वाच माई कंटेंट अगेन,
you are going to come across a very new story
यू आर गोइंग कम अक्रॉस अ वेरी न्यू स्टोरी
that I am very excited to tell
दैट आई एम वेरी एक्साइटेड टू टेल
you.  This is episode 100 of The Prakhar Gupta
यू। दिस इज़ एपिसोड 100 ऑफ़ द प्रखर गुप्ता
Experience.
एक्सपीरियंस।
You are probably close to the 100 crore
यू आर प्रोबेब्ली क्लोज टू द 100 करोड़
viewers that we have on this channel.  This has been an
व्यूअर दैट वी हैव ऑन दिस चैनल। दिस हैज़
absolute dream to live through.  To
बीन एन एब्सोल्यूट ड्रीम टू लिव थ्रू। टू
build for.  This has been bigger,
बिल्ड फॉर। दिस हैज़ बीन
more beautiful, more
बिगर मोर ब्यूटीफुल मोर
meaningful than I thought it would be This has
मीनिंगफुल देन आई थॉट इट वुड बी दिस हैज़
given me some incredible friends, some
गिवेन मी सम इनक्रेडिबल फ्रेंड्स सम
incredible mentees that I get to mentor, some very
इनक्रेडिबल मेंटीस दट आय गेट टू मेंटोर सम
young blood that I like to shape, some very
वेरी यंग ब्लड दैट आई लाइक टू शेप सम वैरी
cool things to talk to my father about Now you have
कूल थिंग्स टू टॉक टू माय फादर अबाउट नाउ
given my father's pride when you
यू हैव गिवेन माय फादर प्राइड व्हेन यू
walk up to him and tell him that I
वॉक अप टू हिम एंड टेल हिम कि मैं आपके
watch your son's content He loves it.  You
बेटे का कंटेंट देखता हूं ही लव्स इट। यू
have made me smile.  Thank you so much.  This is
हैव मेड मी स्माइल। थैंक यू सो मच। दिस इज
a dream and I am going to make this dream
अ ड्रीम एंड आई एम गोइंग टू मेक दिस ड्रीम
bigger and larger for us.  On to the dirt.  See
बिगर एंड लार्जर फॉर अस। ऑन टू दर्स्ट। सी
you.
यू।